<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>hack.write()</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/</link><description>Writing about writing about development.</description><atom:link href="http://hackwrite.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 23:42:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>File Names</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/file-names/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only two hard things in Computer Science: cache invalidation and naming things.&lt;br&gt;
-- Phil Karlton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot help you with cache invalidation.&lt;br&gt;
-- Adam Michael Wood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently saw a question about file names in the &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/episcopalcommunicators/"&gt;Episcopal Communicators Facebook Group&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Question about file names." src="http://hackwrite.com/img/filename-question.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a question about filenames for websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first developed our website, our consultant told me that when we put a file on there, it's important to give the file a date and a unique and descriptive name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While that works for some files, it doesn't for others. It caused me to end up with a lot of old files on my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I changed was that I stopped changing file names. So instead of mileage_rates_2016.pdf, I just call it mileage_rates.pdf. That way every link is correct, everywhere on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when we link to outside websites, like the wider church's site, we end up with obsolete links. Case in point: the Manual of Business Methods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had full_manual_updated_09-30-2013.pdf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now the link is full_manual_updated_012815_0.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there any need to give dates to files like this? It's important for the organization to archive old versions, but is there any need to have unique names so that websites like ours end up with older versions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I summed a few file name best practices, but... I have &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; to say about this topic. File naming is one of those weird little things I have irrationally strong feelings about, and the ubiquity of bad file naming practices is a constant source of rage in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/file-names/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/file-names/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 14:31:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What (and how much) to learn?</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/what-and-how-much-to-learn/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote that you don't need to attain a high-level of coding skill for learning to code to be useful. A technical writer can see substantial ROI from just learning &lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/enough-to-be-dangerous/"&gt;enough to be dangerous&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which raises (not begs!) the question: How much &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; enough? What topics should tech writers know? And how well should we know them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start answering that question, I'd like to expand what we mean by "learn to code" or "knowing how to code" to "developer skills" in general. Too much focus on &lt;em&gt;coding&lt;/em&gt; overlooks the other highly useful things that developers know and do that tech writers can benefit from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/what-and-how-much-to-learn/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/what-and-how-much-to-learn/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Problem with Github Pages</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/github-pages-problem/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I love Github Pages. I run this blog, my &lt;a href="http://adammichaelwood.com"&gt;personal blog&lt;/a&gt;, and my &lt;a href="http://progressivesolemnity.org"&gt;music and liturgy blog&lt;/a&gt; on it. I used it to host &lt;a href="http://docs.botcentral.ai"&gt;documentation for my most recent tech writing gig&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a single writer with moderate or better technical skills looking for a simple hosting solution, it's amazing. But, I've recently realized there's a problem with it that makes it ill-suited for multiple collaborators working on complicated documentation. (Or even, as I discovered, a single writer on more than one machine.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/github-pages-problem/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/github-pages-problem/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 13:50:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Shipping</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/shipping/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My New Year's Resolution --- which I have so far held to --- is to write &lt;em&gt;and publish&lt;/em&gt; every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/shipping/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/shipping/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 14:42:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Data Structures and Philosophy</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/data-structures-and-philosophy/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes bad programming is just bad programming: people write sloppy code, people don't know how things are supposed to work, people forget that binary math is weird sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But often, bad programming is a result of bad philosophy - a fundamental misunderstanding of how meaning is made, or thought works, or how the world is structured. Sometimes the fault is a little less radical, tied to ignorance of some domain-specific facts, but often it's just plain bad philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/data-structures-and-philosophy/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/data-structures-and-philosophy/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 15:26:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On the Design of this Blog</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/on-the-design-of-this-blog/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since I spend almost my entire day in an editor, writing, I've put a bit of effort into getting it to look the way I like. The most important things for my writing experience are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dark theme&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;oversized display font&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;syntax highlighting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relatively narrow text (&amp;lt; 80 column)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;centered text with a decent margin on each side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what my screen looks like when writing a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AMW Post in Editor" src="http://hackwrite.com/img/amw-post-in-editor.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/on-the-design-of-this-blog/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/on-the-design-of-this-blog/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 14:29:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Overriding CSS/LESS Declaration to Reduce One LOC</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/overriding-css-declaration-to-reduce-loc/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;While working on the theme for &lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com"&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;, I was referencing &lt;a href="http://mrcoles.com/demo/markdown-css/"&gt;Markdown CSS&lt;/a&gt;, which makes HTML look like Markdown. (h/t &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ericholscher"&gt;@ericholscher&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://github.com/mrcoles/markdown-css/blob/master/markdown.less"&gt;ran across an interesting (let's call it a) pattern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/overriding-css-declaration-to-reduce-loc/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/overriding-css-declaration-to-reduce-loc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 13:50:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It Should Matter That It's You</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/it-should-matter-that-its-you/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I grew up doing theatre, went to college for theatre, and taught theatre for a few years. Nearly all of my theatre experience --- as a performer, teacher, director, stagehand, designer, or even audience member --- was non-profit and the bulk was non-professional. High school, university, community, non-profit regional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of shows where it didn't seem to matter who had directed it, or who had designed it. So many high school and community theatre shows are bad reproductions of the professional version of the same show. Musicals, comedies, murder mysteries... musical comedy murder mysteries. Names the audience recognizes, with poorly built sets that look pretty much the same as every other production of the show, and costumes assembled from what seems like the same pile of thrift-store refuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/it-should-matter-that-its-you/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/it-should-matter-that-its-you/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 14:06:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Simple Input Validation and Exception Handling in Python</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/simple-input-validation-handling-python/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are doing a simple terminal script in Python, and you need to validate some user-supplied input, you can put the assignment and validation in a &lt;code&gt;try&lt;/code&gt; block inside a &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/simple-input-validation-handling-python/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/simple-input-validation-handling-python/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 14:33:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Enough to Be Dangerous: The Joy of Bad Python</title><link>http://hackwrite.com/posts/enough-to-be-dangerous/</link><dc:creator>Adam Michael Wood</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning to Code&lt;/strong&gt; is all the rage. I don't see any sign that the trend is dying down any time soon. I might as well jump on the bandwagon here and encourage my fellow tech writers to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, a lot of you already code, or are in the process of learning. I once assumed knowing at least some coding was a requirement for being a tech writer. But it seems this isn't entirely the case. Some TWs need to be able to read and write enough code to document APIs and provide code samples --- but apparently (I have learned) most tech writers aren't doing that, and you can fake your way through that if you really need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;strong&gt;if you are among the majority of technical writers that don't code, this post is for you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://hackwrite.com/posts/enough-to-be-dangerous/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hackwrite.com/posts/enough-to-be-dangerous/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 14:31:41 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>